<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<chapter version="5.0"
  xsi:schemaLocation="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook http://www.docbook.org/xml/5.0/xsd/docbook.xsd"
  xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
  xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema" xmlns:xl="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
  xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" xmlns:xhtml="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"
  xmlns:svg="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg" xmlns:mth="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
  xmlns:db="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xml:id="sharing">
  <title>About sharing of
    <?oxy_comment_start author="cecilia" timestamp="20170509T142346+0200" comment="Section requires complete review.
2.27: new sharing dialog in Mtn app.

Future releases: Legacy sharing dialog will be replaced with new in the analytics apps, Users app and Dashboard app."?>objects<?oxy_comment_end?></title>
  <para>This chapter discusses the sharing of entities feature in DHIS2.</para>
  <section>
    <title>Sharing of objects</title>
    <para>Many objects in DHIS2, like reports, charts, maps and indicators, can be shared. DHIS
      supports sharing of metadata or sharing of data. Sharing of metadata means making an object,
      like a report, available for reading or modification to a group of users or to everyone.
      Sharing of data means making the actual data captured available to others, and controlling who
      can capture that kind of data. For instance for reports, the sharing dialog can be opened by
      clicking on the &quot;Sharing settings&quot; button next to each report in the list.
      Implementers can use this feature to allow access to certain objects to only certain user
      groups. Users can use the feature to decide who they would like to share objects (such as
      pivot tables, charts, dashboards, etc) with. </para>
    <para>If sharing is supported for a particular class of objects, a dialog will be available
      called &quot;Sharing settings&quot;, usually available by clicking on the name of the object
      or in the analytics tools, through an icon (Share with other people). Once you have accessed
      the sharing settings for the object you wish to share, a dialog similar to the one below will
      be shown. </para>
    <para>
      <screenshot>
        <title>The new sharing dialog</title>
        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata width="40%" fileref="resources/images/maintainence/mtn_sharing_dialog.png"
              format="PNG" align="center"/>
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </screenshot>
    </para>
    <para>You can share your report with everyone or with a number of user groups. &quot;External
      access&quot; can be enabled to allow this resource to be shared with everyone, including users
      which cannot logon to DHIS2. This is useful for sharing public resources with external
      systems. Note, that if objects are shared externally, then they are visible to anyone who has
      access to the URL which provides the resource without any login credentials. </para>
    <para>Next to &quot;Public access&quot; you can choose your public access option under
      &quot;METADATA&quot;: &quot;No access&quot;, &quot;Can view only&quot; or &quot;Can edit and
      view&quot;, and under &quot;DATA&quot;: &quot;No access&quot;, &quot;Can view data&quot;,
      &quot;Can capture data&quot;. Public access refers to users which are logged into the system.
      Edit also implies deleting the report. </para>
    <para>To share with a group, simply start typing the name of the group and the &quot;Search for
      user groups&quot; input field and select your desired group. Click on the &quot;+&quot; icon
      next to the input field to share with that group. For each group you can set an access option,
      similar to public access.</para>
    <para>Sharing with a user group implies that all users in that group will get access to the
      shared object. To create a user group you can go to the dashboard module and click on
      &quot;Groups&quot;. This will lead you to the list of groups where you can click &quot;Add
      new&quot; in the top right corner. Creating user groups is open for everyone from the
      dashboard module.</para>
  </section>
  <section>
    <title>Metadata sharing and access control</title>
    <para>The objects which support metadata sharing are indicator, indicator group, indicator group
      set, data dictionary, data set, program, standard report, resource, report table, chart, map
      and user group. Out of those objects, report table, chart, map and user group are open for
      everyone to create privately. Private means that the objects are available only to yourself or
      potentially to a number of user groups if you choose to share the object. These objects are
      referred to as &quot;open&quot; objects and can be created by all users. The remaining objects
      require that your user account has the authority to create them. These objects are referred to
      as &quot;non-open&quot; objects.</para>
    <para>A user can be granted the authority to create publicly accessible objects or privately
      accessible objects. In order to create a publicly accessible object (available for viewing or
      editing by anyone) your user account must have the authority to do so. As an example, to
      create a publicly accessible chart, your user must have the &quot;Create public chart&quot;
      authority granted. The authority to create private objects applies only to non-open objects.
      For example, to allow a user to create indicators which will only be accessible to that user
      and not to everyone, the user can be issued with the &quot;Create private indicator&quot;
      authority.</para>
    <para>Sharing a non-open object with another person and let her edit the object requires that
      the person&apos;s user account has the authority for updating that type of objects granted.
      For instance, if you want to let another person edit your indicator, that person&apos;s user
      account must have the &quot;Update indicator&quot; authority granted. This does not apply for
      open objects.</para>
    <para>When you create a new object it will automatically become viewable for everyone if your
      user account has the authority to create public objects. As an example, if you create a
      standard report and you have the &quot;Create public standard report&quot; authority granted,
      the report will become viewable for everyone. If you do not have that authority granted the
      report will be viewable only to yourself. After you have created an object, you may navigate
      to the &quot;Sharing settings&quot; dialog and set your desired access control level.</para>
    <para>If you need a user account which is able to view absolutely all objects you can create a
      user role with the &quot;ALL&quot; authority and assign a user to that role. If you need to
      switch between a &quot;complete&quot; view of objects and a &quot;personal&quot; view of
      objects it is recommended to create two user accounts, one assigned with the &quot;ALL&quot;
      authority and one without.</para>
  </section>
  <section>
    <title>Metadata sharing applied</title>
    <para>The metadata sharing functionality is useful in several scenarios. One use-case is setting
      up a DHIS2 instance for a global organisation with operations in multiple countries. Typically
      the organisation has a set of global data sets, indicators and reports which should apply to
      all countries, while all countries will have the need for country-specific data sets,
      indicators and reports. In this scenario the following approach could work: </para>
    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>Set up one user group for global personnel.</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>Set up a user group for personnel in each country.</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>Create global data sets and reports, make them viewable for everyone and editable for
          the global user group only.</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>Create country-specific data sets and reports, make them viewable and editable for the
          country user group and the global user group only.</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
    <para>This way, the global indicators and reports could be viewed and analysed by everyone, but
      maintained by the global user group only. The country-specific data sets, indicators and
      reports could be viewed and maintained by the country and global personnel, without being
      visible or impacting the system for other countries in the organisation.</para>
    <para>A similar approach could work for a scenario with a donor, multiple funding agencies and
      implementing partners in a country, where user groups could be set up for each of those
      entities. That way each implementing partner could create and share their reports within their
      organisation without affecting or allowing access to others. Reports could also be shared with
      supervisors and funding agencies at the end of reporting periods.</para>
    <para>Another use-case is a country department of health with multiple health programs.
      Typically there is a need for having general reports and charts for the department while
      allowing the health programs to develop specific reports and charts for internal use. This can
      be achieved by creating user groups for each health program. Later, when developing reports
      and charts, these can be made viewable and editable to the program user group only. This way
      the reports will not be visible to other programs and users. This is beneficial because the
      reports are kept internal to the program and because the visible list of reports of other
      users are kept shorter and more relevant.</para>
  </section>
  <section>
    <title>Data sharing and access control</title>
    <para>The objects which support data sharing are data set, tracked entity type, program and
      program stage. The purpose of data sharing is to control which users can capture data, and
      which users can see the data captured.</para>
    <section>
      <title>Data sharing for event based programs</title>
      <para>Applies to the object types of tracked entity type, program and program stage. When
        working with single event programs in event capture, a user will have to possess the
        &quot;DATA:Can view data&quot; sharing level to see the program and its data. Without this
        sharing level, the program and its data will not be visible to the user. When working with
        tracker programs in tracker capture, the user will need to have &quot;DATA:Can view
        data&quot; to both the tracked entity type and program. In case of a tracker program, the
        user will also need &quot;DATA:Can view data&quot; on each program stage individually to be
        able to see the data within the program. To capture data the user needs the &quot;DATA:Can
        capture data&quot; sharing level. <note>
          <para>To see and capture data for a program, a data capture user also needs to report for
            an organisaction unit to where the program has been assigned.</para>
        </note>
      </para>
      <table frame="all">
        <title>Data sharing for tracker programs</title>
        <tgroup cols="4">
          <colspec colname="c1" colnum="1" colwidth="2*"/>
          <colspec colname="c2" colnum="2" colwidth="4*"/>
          <colspec colname="c3" colnum="3" colwidth="4*"/>
          <colspec colname="c4" colnum="4" colwidth="3*"/>
          <thead>
            <row>
              <entry>Object type</entry>
              <entry>Can view data</entry>
              <entry>Can capture data</entry>
              <entry>Comment</entry>
            </row>
          </thead>
          <tbody>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <para><emphasis role="bold">Tracked entity type</emphasis></para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para>
                  <itemizedlist>
                    <listitem>
                      <para>Search for tracked entities with this tracked entity type.</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                      <para>See tracked entity type attribute values for this tracked entity
                        type.</para>
                    </listitem>
                  </itemizedlist>
                </para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para>
                  <itemizedlist>
                    <listitem>
                      <para>Edit visible tracked entity attributes for tracked entity instances of
                        this type.</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                      <para>Register/create new tracked entity instances of this type.</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                      <para>Delete tracked entity instances of this type.</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                      <para>Deactivate/reactivate tracked entity instances of this type.</para>
                    </listitem>
                  </itemizedlist>
                </para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para/>
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <para><emphasis role="bold">Program</emphasis></para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para>
                  <itemizedlist>
                    <listitem>
                      <para>Search for tracked entities within this program.</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                      <para>See tracked entity attributes specific to this program.</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                      <para>See enrollment details for the program.</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                      <para>See notes for the enrollment.</para>
                    </listitem>
                  </itemizedlist>
                </para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para>
                  <itemizedlist>
                    <listitem>
                      <para>Enroll into the program.</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                      <para>Edit enrollment details for the program.</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                      <para>Complete/reopen enrollments into the program.</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                      <para>Add notes for the program.</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                      <para>Edit relationships for the program.</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                      <para>Send message to tracked entity instance.</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                      <para>Delete enrollments in the program.</para>
                    </listitem>
                  </itemizedlist>
                </para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para>Both &quot;Can view data&quot; and &quot;Can capture data&quot; also requires
                  the user to have &quot;Can view data&quot; for the tracked entity type.</para>
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <para><emphasis role="bold">Program stage</emphasis></para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para>
                  <itemizedlist>
                    <listitem>
                      <para>See the program stage and its events and data within an
                        enrollment.</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                      <para>See the program stage notes.</para>
                    </listitem>
                  </itemizedlist>
                </para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para>
                  <itemizedlist>
                    <listitem>
                      <para>Add/schedule/refer a new event within the program stage.</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                      <para>Complete/reopen the events within the program stage.</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                      <para>Edit tracked entity data values within events in the program
                        stage.</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                      <para>Add notes for events in the program stage.</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                      <para>Delete events in the program stage.</para>
                    </listitem>
                  </itemizedlist>
                </para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para>Both &quot;Can view data&quot; and &quot;Can capture data&quot; also requires
                  the user to have &quot;Can view data&quot; for the program and the tracked entity
                  type.</para>
              </entry>
            </row>
          </tbody>
        </tgroup>
      </table>
      <table frame="all">
        <title>Data sharing for single event programs</title>
        <tgroup cols="4">
          <colspec colname="c1" colnum="1" colwidth="2*"/>
          <colspec colname="c2" colnum="2" colwidth="4*"/>
          <colspec colname="c3" colnum="3" colwidth="4*"/>
          <colspec colname="c4" colnum="4" colwidth="3*"/>
          <thead>
            <row>
              <entry>Object type</entry>
              <entry>Can view data</entry>
              <entry>Can capture data</entry>
              <entry>Comment</entry>
            </row>
          </thead>
          <tbody>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <para><emphasis role="bold">Program</emphasis></para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para>
                  <itemizedlist>
                    <listitem>
                      <para>See list of events within the program.</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                      <para>See tracked entity data values for events in the program.</para>
                    </listitem>
                  </itemizedlist>
                </para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para>
                  <itemizedlist>
                    <listitem>
                      <para>Add new events into the program.</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                      <para>Edit data for events in the program.</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                      <para>Delete events in the program.</para>
                    </listitem>
                  </itemizedlist>
                </para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para/>
              </entry>
            </row>
          </tbody>
        </tgroup>
      </table>
    </section>
    <section>
      <title>Data sharing for data sets</title>
      <para>Applies to the object types of data set and category option . When working in Data Entry
        app,  the user will need to have &quot;DATA:Can capture data&quot; to both see and capture
        data in the data set. To save data for an entry field in Data Set users need: <orderedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>Authority: F_DATAVALUE_ADD ( Can add data value )</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>Data Set is shared with "Data: Can capture data"</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>Data Element is shared with "Metadata: Can View"</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>All Category Options used by selected Data Set are shared with "Data: Can capture
              data"</para>
          </listitem>
        </orderedlist><note>
          <para>To see and capture data for a data set, a data capture user also needs to report for
            an organisaction unit to where the data set has been assigned.</para>
        </note>
      </para>
      <table frame="all">
        <title>Data sharing for data sets</title>
        <tgroup cols="4">
          <colspec colname="c1" colnum="1" colwidth="2*"/>
          <colspec colname="c2" colnum="2" colwidth="4*"/>
          <colspec colname="c3" colnum="3" colwidth="4*"/>
          <colspec colname="c4" colnum="4" colwidth="3*"/>
          <thead>
            <row>
              <entry>Object type</entry>
              <entry>Can view data</entry>
              <entry>Can capture data</entry>
              <entry>Comment</entry>
            </row>
          </thead>
          <tbody>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <para><emphasis role="bold">Data set</emphasis></para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para>
                  <itemizedlist>
                    <listitem>
                      <para>View Data Set's data in Analytics</para>
                    </listitem>
                  </itemizedlist>
                </para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para>
                  <itemizedlist>
                    <listitem>
                      <para>Can see DataSet in Data Entry app</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                      <para>Can save data for Data Set using API</para>
                    </listitem>
                  </itemizedlist>
                </para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para>For saving data value in Data Entry app, users also need "Can capture data"
                  for Category Options within selected Data Set.</para>
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry><emphasis role="bold">CategoryOption</emphasis></entry>
              <entry>
                <itemizedlist>
                  <listitem>
                    <para>Can view data values belong to shared Category Option in analytics</para>
                  </listitem>
                </itemizedlist>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <itemizedlist>
                  <listitem>
                    <para>Can save data value for input fields in Data Entry app which belongs to
                      shared Category Options. </para>
                  </listitem>
                </itemizedlist>
              </entry>
              <entry>For CategoryOptionCombo and AttributeOptionCombo to be writable, all belongs
                CategoryOptions must be shared with "Can capture data".</entry>
            </row>
          </tbody>
        </tgroup>
      </table>
    </section>
  </section>
</chapter>
